A Guide to the R. Bolling Batte papers, 1921-1996
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
R. Bolling Batte papers, 1921-1996
The Library of Virginia
51386
.7 cubic feet and 2 boxes
R. Bolling Batte
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Purchased from Crown Collectibles, Chesterfield, Virginia.
Biographical Information
Robert Bolling Batte was born 13 August 1906 in Norfolk, Virginia, to Samuel Bassett French Batte (1876-1933) and Mary Campbell Jones Batte (1878-1957). He graduated from Virginia Military Institute in 1928. Batte served in the Army, then worked for the Chesapeake and Potomac Telephone Company before World War II. When the United States entered World War II, Batte returned to military service and was stationed in Germany after the war ended. He returned to Chesapeake and Potomac after the war, and earned a law degree in the early 1950s. After retiring from Chesapeake and Potomac in 1969, he was a partner in Batte, Batte, and Wicker. Batte married first Elizabeth Jacquiline Bacot (b. 1908) on 30 December 1933. He married second Frances Harrison Drummond (1910-1996) on 12 November 1938, and they had three children. Batte died in Richmond, Virginia, 3 June 1996, and was buried in Elmwood Cemetery in Norfolk.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1921-1996, of R. Bolling Batte (1906-1996) of Richmond and Chesterfield County, Virginia, consisting of appointments, articles, cards, certificates, clippings, correspondence, deposit books, diplomas, envelopes, grade reports, invitations, military orders, newspapers, pamphlets, photographs, powers of attorney, receipts, and other papers concerning R. Bolling Batte (1906-1996) of Norfolk, Richmond, and Chesterfield County, Virginia, and covering Batte's personal life and his military service, as well as his son's, Robert Bolling Batte IV (1943-), education and efforts to defer his military service.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I: Batte correspondence, 1921-1985
Series II: Batte-Neumann letters, 1946-1947
Series III: R. Bolling Batte IV, 1943-1977
Series IV: General papers, 1951-1996
Contents List
- Series I: Batte correspondence, 1921-1985., Extent: 1 box. (Box 1)
  Batte correspondence, 1921-1985, contains cards, clippings, correspondence, envelopes, invitations, and receipts, mainly to R. Bolling Batte from his mother, Mary Campbell Jones Batte (1878-1957), his wife, Frances Harrison Drummond Batte (1910-1996), family members, and friends, discussing family and personal news, including the birth of Batte's third child, Frances, and his first child's, Lucy's, first year of school; life in Norfolk, Virginia, New Orleans, Louisiana, and elsewhere; commenting on World War II and its events both in the United States and in Europe; and briefly mentioning genealogical research.
  - Letters, 1921. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letters, 1930-1938, 193[-]. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters, 1942-1944. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters, June-September 1945. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters, October 1945. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letters, November-December 1945. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letters, January 1946. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letters, February 1946. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Letters, March, August 1946, 194[-]. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letters, 1950-1958. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Letters, 1960-1963. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Letters, 1964. (Box 1)
  - Letters, 1965. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Letters, 1967-1969, 196[-]. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Letters, 1970, 1973, 1985. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Letters, undated. (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Series II: Batte-Neumann letters, 1946-1947., Extent: 1 box. (Box 1)
  Batte-Neumann letters, 1946-1947, contain correspondence between R. Bolling Batte and Ursula Neumann of Berlin-Friedenau, Germany, regarding personal and family news. Neumann, whom Bolling befriended in Germany after World War II, offers a view of life in post-war Germany. Many of her letters are in German.
  - Batte to Neumann, 1946, undated. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Neumann to Batte, March-April 1946. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Neumann to Batte, June-August 1946. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Neumann to Batte, November-December 1946. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Neumann to Batte, January-March 1947. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Neumann to Batte, May-June 1947. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Neumann to Batte, including incomplete letters, undated. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Die Neue Zeitung, 7 July 1947. (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Series III: R. Bolling Batte IV, 1943-1977., Extent: 1 box. (Box 2)
  R. Bolling Batte IV papers, 1943-1977, contain appointments, articles, certificates, correspondence, diplomas, grade reports, military orders, pamphlets, powers of attorney, receipts, reports, and other papers regarding R. Bolling Batte IV's (1943-) personal life, religious life, and education. Papers also concern Batte's education at the Virginia Military Institute, his efforts to defer his military service during the Vietnam War, his departure for Canada, and his interest in receiving amnesty. Papers also include account information on life insurance policies with New York Life and the Travelers Insurance Companies, as well as certificates, deposit book, and receipts regarding investments and savings.
  - Certificates--religious, 1943, 1952-1955. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Certificates--education (St. Paul's Church School), 1952-1958. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Letters, 1954-[1968]. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - VMI--letters and papers, 1959-1963. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - VMI--letters and papers, 1964, undated. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - VMI--receipts (including payment for chest x-rays), 1960-1964. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - VMI--grades, 1961-1964. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - VMI--articles, 1962, 1964. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Military papers, 1964. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Military papers, 1965. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Military papers, 1966-1967. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Military papers, 1977, undated. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous papers (YWCA camp, Cub Scout pamphlet, driver's education certificate, College of William and Mary report card, power of attorney), 1951-1967. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Insurance policy with New York Life Insurance Company, 1962, 1967. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Insurance policy with Travelers Insurance Company, 1960-1967. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Financial papers, 1956-1964. (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Series IV: General papers, 1951-1996., Extent: 1 box. (Box 2)
  General papers, 1951-1996, contain an article about R. Bolling Batte's visit to Adolph Hitler's death site, ca. 1987; and two obituaries, 1996, for Batte; miscellaneous financial and insurance records, including insurance papers regarding a burglary claim by Batte; and a photograph of Batte and his daughter Lucinda "Lucy" Batte.
  - Article and obituaries, ca. 1987, 1996. (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Financial and insurance papers (letter, Richmond Federal Savings and Loan, Travelers Insurance Company, bank stub, insurance claim and correspondence, 1951-1981, undated. (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Photograph of Batte with his daughter Lucinda "Lucy" Campbell Batte, undated. (Box 2, Folder 19)